this now is the third challenge/complication
that stems
from multicore/multiprocessor architectures
and it's the
one about where to place the operating system
let's say we have four CPUs plus some memory
that is shared
by all the CPUs
where do we place the data the text the functions
of the
operating system and who runs
who executes
these functions
so the operating system basically well we
can go in different
ways here
something we could do might look strange but
there might
be cases in which this actually makes sense
is to say well
we take the memory a portion of it
we use it for keeping the code of the operating
system
and then we partition the rest into disjoint
chunks
in this case 4 because we have 4 CPUs and
we run one operating
system for CPU we have available
so basically it's like running n computers
but within
the same computer where n is the number of CPUs here
the operating systems are not sharing anything
well they
are sharing the portion of code but this
is something you
just read you don't modify
but then the data each operating system has
its own portion
of the memory so it's perfectly fine
the problem with this which is the general
problem you have
with things that are simple is that most of
the time they
might be inefficient
so if one operating system has a lot to do
and the rest has
nothing to do well that's basically it since each
operating
system has its own data the one that has a lot
to do cannot
really get help from the other CPUs
so it's not really that efficient
but there is a more serious problem that is
the one of consistency
data in this case can become inconsistent
especially with
buffers if one of the operating system reads
a file from
the disc and keeps it in memory because it's
going to do
something with it and then another operating
system that
is a different one and it's not talking with
the first one
also reads the same file and then writes it
back changing
it now the first operating system has no idea
that the
file has changed
so there are inconsistent copies of the same
information
because here there is no sharing no communication
between
the different operating systems
so you see it's potentially dangerous if they
are operating
on the same resources
for instance the discs as I just mentioned well we
can do something
else we could say okay we don't run n operating
systems
in parallel
we just run one and we actually take one CPU
and we dedicate
it to the operating system
so this is the master this CPU only executes
code that belongs
to the operating system and all the other
CPUs can run the
code that belongs to the processes of the user
and various processes
that are running at the operating system
we don't need to share memory between different
operating
systems there is a single operating system
everything needs
to go through the master CPU
so now we are solving the problem with data
and consistency
because since everything needs to go through
the same entity
the same core which is the one that runs the
OS (not CPU!) everything
will be consistent
the problem here is again okay you solve a
problem but
you're still trying to do something simple
and this also has a price
and the price here is that it's very easy
to bottleneck
such a system you will not really scale
the system to
a lot of cores because you only have one master
and when that one it's saturated
all the slave cores have nothing to do
if all of the slave cores want to do some
kind of input
output and they need to talk with the operating
system then
they can only go as fast as the master core
is able to handle
all the requests
so what you can do which is what you do in
practice in your
operating system is that you don't really
say well there
is one CPU that is the one that runs the operating
system on one
core and the rest are slaves
any core can at any time run either code that
belongs to
the operating system or code that belongs
to an user process
and they share memory
now if you do something like this you might
end up having
the same problem with consistency we had in
the beginning
if they operate on the same data without coordination
you
can end up with inconsistent data
now it's even worse because this inconsistent
data might
actually belong to the operating system itself
since all
the cores can run operating system code
and they all share
the same memory
so basically here the problem is that you
have concurrent
access even to the kernel not just to physical
devices
like the disk as I mentioned before
now how do you manage this?
well you need some kind of synchronization
primitive so
that you make sure that if something is sensitive
inside
the kernel you don't modify it concurrently
without taking care of the risks of this concurrent
modifications
you could go for just using a big lock
so basically whenever you want to do something
with the
operating system first you need to acquire
a lock and then
you are the only one that is able to run the
the code that
belongs to the operating system
but you see that if you do something like
this then you
are basically going back to the master-slave
now you don't have always the same core
that is the one that runs the operating system
code
but it's still only one core at a time that
can be the one
that runs the operating system code so a big
lock is not really
an option
what you want to do is to have critical regions
and fine
grained parallelism
but as you would see in the next lectures
with marina it
complicates the matter a lot
okay you need to use / you can use several synchronization
primitives and you need to do it carefully
because you can
end up in deadlocks
okay i guess you have heard these terms before
but if you
have not don't worry too much you will understand
better
all these things in the following lectures